A Guide to the Robert C. Schnitzer Collection
Copyright George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Robert C. Schnitzer Collection
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Schnitzer 001
4.5 cubic feet or 6.75 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert C. Schnitzer (b. 1906) is a former actor, producer, educator, and theater administrator. As a young actor in New York City, Schnitzer appeared in or stage managed The Brothers Karamazov, Hamlet, An Enemy of the People, Richelieu, Henry V, Richard III, Caponsacchi, Macbeth, and Cyrano de Bergerac. From 1936 to 1939, Schnitzer was Delaware's State Director and Deputy National Director of the WPA's Federal Theatre Project.
Schnitzer later joined the American National Theater and Academy (ANTA) as general manager for the Experimental Theater in New York, which returned to the New York theater scene under the auspices of ANTA in 1947. The ANTA-sponsored performances managed by Mr. Schnitzer included the first American production of Hamlet to be presented at Elsinore, Denmark; the first European tour of the American Ballet Theatre in 1950; and from 1951 to 1953, three Berlin festivals that showcased American talent such as the Theatre Guild's Oklahoma, the Hall Johnson Choir, and the Julliard String Quartet.
In 1954, Mr. Schnitzer took over as general manager for the International Exchange Program through which ANTA helped promote and sponsor cultural exchanges in cooperation with the U.S. State Department. The hundreds of overseas productions arranged by Mr. Schnitzer ran the gamut from college choirs and athletes to notables such as Marian Anderson, the Dave Brubeck Quartet, and the New York Philharmonic Orchestra under the direction of Leonard Berstein. Many of these performers played to audiences in Berlin, Moscow, and other locations behind the Iron Curtain.
In 1960, Mr. Schnitzer became the general manager for the American Repertory Company, set up by the Theatre Guild at the request of the U.S. Government to export the best in American theater. He arranged for three plays - The Skin of Our Teeth, The Miracle Worker, and The Glass Menagerie - to tour 28 countries in Europe and South America in 1961. The company included the famous actress Helen Hayes. During the 1970s he was head of the University of Michigan's Professional Theatre Program.
In the early 1980s, Mr. Schnitzer donated to George Mason University papers and records from his service as a deputy administrator for the WPA Federal Theatre Project.
Scope and Content Information
Included in the Robert C. Schnitzer Papers are: textual materials (subject files, correspondence, memoranda, etc) re: ANTA overseas productions; photographs of ANTA theater troupe in Europe 1951 and 1955, and other ANTA personnel; 1950s and 1960s promotional posters for ANTA overseas productions; newspaper clippings re: ANTA performances in Europe; prompt script to the play "Skin of Our Teeth" starring Helen Hayes; working papers and other materials re: Schnitzer's work with the University of Michigan, Professional Theatre Program Total volume of collection is 4.5 cubic feet or 6.75 linear feet.
Arrangement
Topic/subject
Contents List
- Robert C. Schnitzer Collection
  - ANTA- State Department 1960-1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Robert Schnitzer Move From ANTA to the Theater Guild 1960 (Box Box 1)
  - '65 Germany [1965] (Box Box 1)
  - Germany 1965 Guest Tour 1965 (Box Box 1)
  - Europe (and others) '65,'66,etc. [1965,1966] (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Pamphlet: Wiesbaden Germany (Box Box 2)
  - Postcards: Europe (Box Box 2)
  - Street Maps: Europe 1950 (Milan, Genoa, Zurich, Florence) (Box Box 2)
  - Tourist Pamphlets (Venice, Turin, Zurich, The Hague, Amsterdam) (Box Box 2)
  - Menu and Table Plan: 22nd International Congress, P.E.N. Club; 8/19/50 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - [Flight Report: Sabena Airlines] (Box Box 2)
  - Work Permits 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - [Miscellaneous Items (re: Europe 1950)] [1 of 2] [1950] (Box Box 2)
  - [Miscellaneous Items (re: Europe 1950)] [ 2 of 2] 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Programs/Playblls: Europe 1950 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Programs/Playbills: Europe 1950 [2 of 3] 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - Programs/Playbills: Europe 1950 [3 of 3] 1950 (Box Box 2)
  - National Theater Assembly 1951 (Box Box 2)
  - Photographs: Europe 1950 [1950] (Box Box 3)
    Youskeuitch, I., Meister, B., Kaye, N., Chapin, Lerie, N., Alouso, Schnitzer, R., Cannon
  - Berlin 1951 (Box Box 3)
    Ginder, C., Westermarm, T., Res, Breen, Doliymfle, J.
  - Berlin 1951 (Box Box 3)
    Cliou, H., Johnson, H.
  - Berlin 1951 (Box Box 3)
    Claire, L., Seldes, M., Lawrence, E., Anderson, J., McClintic, G., dal Porto, L., Breen, Res, Doliymfle, Gossner, Johnson, H.
  - Berlin 1951 (Box Box 3)
    Holm, C., McClintick, G., Anderson, J., McCloy, J.
  - Berlin 1951 (Box Box 3)
    Johnson, P., Holm, C., Asond, R., Marlo, M.,Grinder,P., Libmoll, M., Mathewson, Anderson, J.,
  - Berlin 1951 (Box Box 3)
    Schmoll, W., Johnson, P., Rawlings, J., Austin, H., Platz, Res, Enters, A.,Doliymfle, J.
  - Judith Anderson (Box Box 3)
    Anderson, J., Res
  - Virginia Innes- Brown (Box Box 3)
    Innes-Brown, V.,
  - Robert W. Dowling--Virginia Innes- Brown (Box Box 3)
    Dowling, R., Inner-Brown, V.
  - European Tour (Box Box 3)
    Cirmey and Schnitzer
  - France (Box Box 3)
    Havoc, J., Julien, A., Dillon, Schnitzer, Cizney
  - Hamlet (Box Box 3)
    Breen, R.
  - McIlvaine Farewell 1956 (Box Box 3)
    Farewell, I., Schnitzer, W.
  - Miscellaneous (Box Box 3)
    Litori, Heller, Cisney, Schnitzer, Williams, C., Ilinski, J.
  - Porgy and Bess Company (Box Box 3)
  - South America 1956 (Box Box 3)
    Dalnymple, J., Res
  - Stratford- Summer 1957 (Box Box 3)
    Daleymfle, J.
  - Theatre Guild/ANTA--Repertory Company (Box Box 3)
  - Soviet Arts Seminar (Box Box 4)
  - R.C.S inspection tour South America for possible ANTA bookings (Box Box 4)
  - Special (Box Box 4)
  - Amrepco-Hotel, travel, "extra-curricular activities" (Box Box 4)
  - Customs-Am Rep Co. (Box Box 4)
  - Itinerary-Am Rep Co Latin Amer. tour (Box Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box Box 4)
  - Heller (Box Box 4)
  - How to be an Empresario (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Guild (Langner, Caro, etc.) and Schnitzer--tour operation (Box Box 4)
  - Experimental Theatre (Box Box 5)
  - Experimental Theatre (Box Box 5)
  - Experimental Theatre (Box Box 5)
  - Experimental Theatre (Box Box 5)
  - Experimental Theatre (Box Box 5)
  - Current Film Periodicals in English (Box Box 5)
  - Misc. Get? See? (Box Box 5)
  - Get (Box Box 5)
  - NYU Seminars (Box Box 5)
  - Ballet Theatre (Box Box 5)
  - News clippings (Box Box 5)
  - New clippings (Box Box 5)
  - Reviews (Box Box 6)
  - Hamlet/Denmark (Box Box 6)
  - Hamlet/Denmark (Box Box 6)
  - Hamlet/Denmark (Box Box 6)
  - Hamlet/Denmark--Hamlet/Festival Production (Box Box 6)
  - N.T.C (Box Box 6)
  - Breen, R. misc--New Select. Serv. Card After discharge (Box Box 6)
  - ANTA 1949-1953 (Box Box 6)
  - Berlin 1952--Anta-Ices (International Cultural Exchange (Box Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box Box 6)
    Denwent, C., Schonceit,L., Breen, R., Callowdway, C., Schnitzer, R., Hayes, H., Anderson, J.,Holm, C., Martin, M.,Ormandy, E.
  - The Cultural-Cooperation Program (Box Box 7)
  - Blueprint of Summer Theater 1950 Supplement [1950] (Box Box 7)
  - American National Ballet Theater-European Tour (Box Box 7)
  - Berlin Arts Festival (Box Box 7)
  - Workshop NCBI (Box Box 7)
  - [Rough Verse in Rough Faith and Letters] (Box Box 7)
  - [Breen: Resignation] (Box Box 7)
  - Thirty first Annual Dinner: White House Correspondents Asso. (Box Box 7)
  - [The Will Geev Theatricum Botanicum and others] (Box Box 7)
  - University/ Resident Theatre Association, Inc. NY (Box Box 7)
  - [International Exchange Program] (Box Box 7)
  - Scrap Book (Box Box 7)
  - Berkshire and others (Box Box 7)
  - Barter Theatre (Box Box 7)
  - [South America: 1956] 1956 (Box Box 7)
  - [Bikel, Theodore: Letter 9/7/95] (Box Box 7)
  - [Barter Theatre] (Box Box 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Tours 1950's-1990's (Box Box 8)
  - [Newspaper Clippings] Ballet Theatre 1950 (Box Box 8)
  - [Newspaper Clippings] Berlin: U.S. Ballet at Festival [1950] (Box Box 8)
  - [Newspaper Clippings] American Ballet [1950] (Box Box 8)
  - [Newspaper Clippings] (German Language) 1950 (Box Box 8)
  - [Newspaper Clippings] (German Language: American Ballet) [1950] (Box Box 8)
  - International Exchange Program(ANTA)Progress Reports: Volume 1 November 1954- June 1956 (Box Box 9)
    - Progress Report 1 November 9, 1954
    - Progress Report 2 November 22, 1954
    - Progress Report 3 December 8, 1954
    - Progress Report 4 January 5, 1955
    - Progress Report 5 January 18, 1955
    - Progress Report 6 February 1, 1955
    - Progress Report 7 February 14, 1955
    - Progress Report 8 March 1, 1955
    - Progress Report 9 March 16, 1955
    - Progress Report 10 March 30, 1955
    - Progress Report 11 April 13, 1955
    - Progress Report 12 April 27, 1955
    - Progress Report 13 May 11, 1955
    - Progress Report 14 May 25, 1955
    - Progress Report 15 August 2, 1955
    - Progress Report 16 September 13, 1955
    - Progress Report 17 October 4, 1955
    - Progress Report 18 October 26, 1955
    - Progress Report 19 November 16, 1955
    - Progress Report 20 November 30, 1955
    - Progress Report 21 December 14, 1955
    - Progress Report 22 January 10, 1956
    - Progress Report 23 January 24, 1956
    - Progress Report 24 February 21, 1956
    - Progress Report 25 March 6, 1956
    - Progress Report 26 March 20, 1956
    - Progress Report 27 April 17, 1956
    - Progress Report 28 June 5, 1956
    - Progress Report 29 June 26, 1956
  - International Exchange Program (ANTA): Progress Reports: Volume 2 July 1956- August 1957 (Box Box 9)
    - Progress Report 30 July 25, 1956
    - Progress Report 31 August 7, 1956
    - Progress Report 32 August 21, 1956
    - Progress Report 33 September 4, 1956
    - Progress Report 34 September 26, 1956
    - Progress Report 35 October 16, 1956
    - Progress Report 36 October 29, 1956
    - Progress Report 37 November 13, 1956
    - Progress Report 38 November 27, 1956
    - Progress Report 39 December 11, 1956
    - Progress Report 40 January 4, 1956 [1957]
    - Progress Report 41 January 18, 1957
    - Progress Report 42 February 1, 1957
    - Progress Report 43 February 15, 1957
    - Progress Report 44 March 15, 1957
    - Progress Report 45 March 29, 1957
    - Progress Report 46 April 11, 1957
    - Progress Report 47 May 31, 1957
    - Progress Report 48 June 21, 1957
    - Progress Report 49 July 18, 1957
    - Progress Reports 50 August 8, 1957
  - International Cultural Exchange Service (ANTA): Volume 3: Progress Reports September 1957-July 1960 (Box Box 9)
    - Progress Report 51 September 30, 1957
    - Progress Report 52 October 15, 1957
    - Progress Report 53 October 24, 1957
    - Progress Report 54 November 18, 1957
    - Progress Report 55 January 20, 1958
    - Progress Report 56 Sup March 11, 1958
    - Progress Report 56 February 28, 1958
    - Progress Report 57 [March 24, 1958]
    - Progress Report 58
    - Progress Report 59 November 7, 1958
    - Project Proposal 60 July- October 1959
    - Project Proposal 61 May 8, 1959
    - Project Proposal 62 May 11, 1959
    - Project Proposal 63 April 13, 1959
    - Project Proposal 64 June 25, 1959
    - Project Proposal 65 August 3 - October 11
    - Project Proposal 66 September 15, 1959
    - Project Proposal 67 October 28, 1959
    - Project Proposal 68 December 9, [1959]
    - Project Proposal 69 December 14, 1959
    - Project Proposal 70 February 3, 1960
    - Proposal to James Magdans 71 March 2, 1960
    - Preliminary Project Proposal 72 March 21, 1960
    - Project Proposal 73 April 7, 1960
    - Project Proposal 74 April 28, 1960
    - Project Proposal 75 May 6, 1960
    - Project Proposal 76 June 3, 1960
    - Preliminary Project Proposal 77 July 14, 1960